today we're gonna do some titration calculations
consider the following acid-base
reaction we have hydrochloric acid and
sodium hydroxide yielding sodium
chloride and water if 50 milliliters of
an HCl solution with unknown
concentration are titrated with zero
point two five zero molar sodium
hydroxide and then if it takes 35 point
two three milliliters of base to reach
the equivalence point what was the
concentration of the HCL solution so if
you're not sure how to approach this go
ahead and check out my tutorial on
titration and when you're ready give it a try.
so let's put our reaction up top and
then what we need to remember about the
equivalence point is that it is the
point where the moles of acid equals
moles of base so it is the point where
precisely all of the acid has been
neutralized by the base so it is telling
us something about stoichiometry when
the equivalence point is reached so
since we want to find out the moles of
acid let's find the moles of base so
let's take our volume of base we have
thirty five point two four milliliters
of base that were required to reach the
equivalence point and let's first
convert that into leaders so dividing by
a thousand milliliters we have 0.03 five
to four liters of Base to reach the
equivalence point now since we have the
concentration of that base we can
convert liters into moles so let's take
our liters of base and multiply by 0.25
zero multiplied not means that was zero
point zero zero eight eight one moles of
base that were required to reach the
point now we have to look at the
stoichiometric ratio the acid in the
base are in a one-to-one ratio so that
means if that many moles of base were
required to reach the equivalence point
then we multiply by one mole of acid
over one mole of base and we get that
same number of moles back for the acid
so when the equivalence point was
reached that many moles of base had
precisely neutralized that many moles of
acid and that is the number of moles of
acid that were in the solution initially
for the HCl solution so now all we have
to do is convert that many moles of acid
into a concentration and so
concentration is moles per liter so we
take our moles of acid and we divide by
0.0500 liters because we know we had
fifty point zero milliliters of acid we
knew the volume we just didn't know the
concentration so that many moles over
that many liters gives us 0.176 moles
per liter or point 176 molar HCl which
was the concentration of our unknown HCl solution.